A Guide to the Papers of Mark Twain, 1862-1946
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series III: Documents
  - Memorandum of agreement between American Publishing Company and New England Society, signed by A. R. Keller for the latter, 1899 January 11; TDS, 2 p. (Box 8)
    Re marketing the uniform set of Mark Twain works.
  - B. West Clinedinst to [Frank E. Bliss], American Publishing Company, 1899 February 3; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for 6 drawings for Roughing It and for 2 additional drawings.
  - Frederick Burr Opper to [Frank E. Bliss ], American Publishing Company, 1899 February 8; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for 6 drawings for Sketches New and Old.
  - Dan Beard to [Frank E. Bliss], American Publishing Company, 1899 May 29; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for 5 wash drawings made over old pen drawings [for The Connecticut Yankee ].
  - Edmund H. Garrett to [Frank E. Bliss], American Publishing Company, 1899 July 1; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for 2 drawings for Life on the Mississippi: "An escaped Archangel" and "Steamboat a' comin."
  - Dan Beard to Frank E. Bliss, [American Publishing Company], 1899 October 6; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for 2 washed repainted illustrations for Tom Sawyer Abroad and photo engraving plates.
  - F. Luis Moran to [Frank E. Bliss,] American Publishing Company, 1902 August 18; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for 3 drawings for volume 23 of Mark Twain uniform set.
  - Contract between Mark Twain and Harper & Brothers, 1902 October 22; TDS, 2 p. (Box 8)
    Re publication of "A Double-Barreled Detective Story."
  - Contract between Mark Twain and Harper & Brothers, 1902 October 22; TDS, 2 p. (Box 8)
    For publication of "The Man That Corrupted Hadleyburg."
  - Royalties paid Mark Twain 1901-02, [ca. 1902]; TD List, 1 p. (Box 8)
    Listing of Harper & Brothers ' royalty payments to Mark Twain in 1901-02.
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1903 April 7; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for payment in full for "Amended Obituaries" sold by MacAlister to Lloyd's Weekly. (originally enclosed with ALS 1903 April 7 and May 8 Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister )
  - Doubleday, Page & Company with AN, 1903 August 12; T Memo, 1 p. (Box 8)
    Notes concerning publication of Mark Twain books with AN concerning same.
  - "Some Conditions Yet to be Agreed Upon", 1903 September 15; TD, 1 p. (Box 8)
    Concerns payments and publication rights between Mark Twain and Olivia L. Clemens and Harper & Brothers and the American Publishing Company.
  - Indenture between Olivia L. Clemens to Charles A. Gardiner, 1903 October 14; TD (copy), 6 p. (Box 8)
    Re leasing of Westchester County, New York, property to Gardiner.
  - Power of Attorney of Mark Twain to Henry H. Rogers, 1903 October 20; PDS, 1 p. (Box 8)
  - Power of attorney of Mark Twain to Henry H. Rogers, 1903 October 20; TDS, 2 p. (Box 8)
  - William H. Hoyt & Company to Olivia L. Clemens, 1903 October 20; D, 1 p. (Box 8)
    Bill for commission on rental for 1 year to Charles A. Gardiner (for Westchester County, New York, property).
  - Contract between Mark Twain, Olivia L. Clemens, and Harper & Brothers with 2 TL copies and 1 T Memo, 1903 October 22-23; TD (copy), 16 p. (Box 8)
    Re exclusive publishing rights for Harper & Brothers to: The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn; A Connecticut Yankee in King Arthur's Court; Tom Sawyer Abroad; The Prince and the Pauper; Life on the Mississippi; The Stolen White Elephant, Etc.; The £1,000,000 Bank Note; Library of Wit and Humor; A Californian's Tale; Tragedy of Pudd'nhead Wilson; Innocents Abroad; The Gilded Age; Roughing It; A Tramp Abroad; Tom Sawyer Detective; Volume of Short Stories; How to Tell a Story; A Double-Barreled Detective Story; The Man That Corrupted Hadleyburg; Following the Equator and any of Mark Twain's other works not listed; covers discount sales, royalties, copyrights, and advertising. With T Memo that shifts date to November 1 1903 for convenience of payment; copy of TL 1903 October 23 Mark Twain and Olivia L. Clemens to American Publishing Company re contract with Harper & Brothers; and copy of TL 1903 October 23 Mark Twain and Olivia L. Clemens to Harper & Brothers authorizing payment of 1/2 royalties for The Gilded Age to estate of Charles Dudley Warner.
  - Frederick Dielmann to [Frank E. Bliss], American Publishing Company, 1904 August 23; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for (unspecified) drawings.
  - Peter Newell to [Frank E. Bliss,] American Publishing Company, 1904 October 10; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for one drawing of Their Pilgrimage, vol. X.
  - Frank E. Bliss to Peter Newell, 1904 October 12; Check (Box 8)
    Check for $100.
  - Edmund H. Garrett to Houghton, Mifflin & Company, 1904 October 15; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for signing proofs.
  - Agreement between Mark Twain and Ralph D. Ashcroft, 1909 March 13; TDS, 2 p. (Box 8)
    Re agreement to let Ashcroft supervise Twain's household affairs and expenditures and his financial affairs in general. Notarized.
  - Agreement between Mark Twain ( Mark Twain Company ) and Ralph D. Ashcroft, 1909 March 13; TDS, 3 p. (Box 8)
    Re agreement to make Ashcroft Twain's business manager and financial manager of his household and The Mark Twain Company. Notarized.
  - Agreement between Mark Twain and Isabel V. Lyon, 1909 March 13; TDS, 2 p. (Box 8)
    Agreement for Isabel V. Lyon to be Twain's literary and social secretary. Notarized.
  - Agreement between Mark Twain and Isabel V. Lyon, 1909 March 13; TDS, 2 p. (Box 8)
    Agreement for Isabel V. Lyon to write Life and Letters of Mark Twain. Notarized.
  - Dodd, Mead & Company to Dana S. Ayer, 1910 May 28; Receipt (Box 8)
    Received on approval one Mark Twain "A Murder and a Marriage."
  - C. Allan Gilbert to [Frank E. Bliss,] American Publishing Company, n.d.; Receipt (Box 8)
    Receipt for drawing of Golden House.
- Series IV: Photographs, Images, and Illustrations
  - Mark Twain, 16 prints of photographs of Mark Twain at various ages, in various poses, [1859-1894]
  - Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing left, brown tone; on verso printed "Gurney" and coat of arms, [1868]
  - Mark Twain standing face front between Josh Billings on the left and Petroleum V. Nasby on right, by H. G. Smith of Boston; picture cut into oval shape; with AN n.d. Frank E. Bliss to Unknown re location of photographs, [1869 November]
  - Print of etching of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing right, by W. H. W. Bicknell. 2 copies; one copy dated, [1871]
  - Print of etching of Mark Twain seated with Clara and Susy Clemens by W. H. W. Bicknell, 1877; Print
  - Photograph of photograph of Olivia, Susy and Clara Clemens; oval portrait photo by Franz Haenstaengl of Munich, Germany, [ca. 1878]
  - Mark Twain, facing right, oval photograph, sepia tone, [1880]
  - Mark Twain, facing right, oval photograph, sepia tone, [1881?]; Warren's Portraits, 465 Washington St., Boston; inscribed by Twain to Miss Koto; dated February.12, 1881 (Box 8)
  - Mark Twain and George Washington Cable, both standing; sepia tone; signed by both men; photograph damaged, [1881]
  - Print of photograph of Mark Twain, facing right, oval picture, sepia tone, [1882-1883]; Print
  - Mark Twain, head and shoulders, right profile; signed "very truly yours", [1884]; Photograph S
  - Mark Twain, in white suit, seated right profile, [1884]
  - Print of photograph of Mark Twain, in white suit, seated right profile, with printed signature, [1884]; Print
  - Print from a photograph of a bust of Mark Twain by Karl Gerhardt, 1884. 3 copies, [after 1884]; Print
  - Mark Twain with Olivia, Clara, Jean and Susy on the ombra of their Hartford, CT, home, [1884]
  - Mark Twain and George Washington Cable, both standing, one hand in pocket; sepia tone photograph; signed by both men, [1884]; Photograph S
  - 4 prints of 2 views from photograph of Mark Twain seated, full face, by Elson, Boston. 1 signed, [1891]
  - Olivia L. Clemens, 2 photographs facing left, 1 photograph full face, by Eddowes Bros., New York, NY, 1893; Photographs
  - Mark Twain in bed, [1895 June 13]
    Mounted on card with ALS 1895 June 13 Mark Twain to Frank Leslie.
  - Mark Twain in bed, [1895 June 13]
  - Mark Twain, Clara and Olivia with James B. Pond, taken during 1895 train trip from Cleveland across U.S. northwest to Vancouver B.C. With 2 photographs of Mark Twain in his London home, 1 seated facing right, 1 seated facing right with Clara standing behind chair, taken by James B. Pond in 1897. Includes notes by James B. Pond on photographs. 34 photographs, 1895 July 17-August 23; Photographs
  - Print of photograph of Mark Twain on rustic porch standing and leaning against porch support, with caption "Announcement Without Words" and signature of Mark Twain, 1895 August 22; Print S
  - Olivia L. Clemens, head and shoulders, by The Falk Studio, Melbourne and Sydney, Australia; inscribed "Very truly yours Olivia L. Clemens ", [1895 September]; Photograph S
  - Mark Twain, head and shoulders facing left, by Falk Studios, Melbourne, Australia; signed S.L.C. and M.T. with inscription to Mr. Parday, 1896 January 24; Photograph S
  - Four photographs of Mark Twain, 1 seated facing left in dark suit, 3 with top hat but different views, by Alfred Ellis of London, [1896-97]; Photographs
  - Mark Twain, in pin striped coat with vest, by [Alfred] Ellis, London, with Mark Twain's signature, [1897 June]; Photograph S
  - Magazine photograph of Mark Twain, [1897 June]; Clipping
  - Composite photograph of a black man and boy driving a cart with a picture of Mark Twain on a chair imposed on cart by Thomas S. Frisbie (with facsimile ALS 1897 October 25 Mark Twain to Thomas S. Frisbie )
  - Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing right, by J. Loewy of Vienna; with signature, 1898 May 16; Photograph S
  - Magazine photograph of Mark Twain by Marceau of Boston, [post 1898 October]; Clipping
  - Print of oil painting of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing right, by Spiridon. 2 copies, 1 signed, [1898-1899]; Print S
  - Print of photograph of Mark Twain; "from portrait series No. 283 The Book News Monthly", 1899; Print
  - Mark Twain, facing slightly left, on wood pedestal, inscribed with Mark Twain across lower front, by A. Weinert; back of bust marked "The Henry Bonard Bronze Co. Founders N.Y. 1899." With one photograph of bust, Bronze Bust
  - Mark Twain, seated indoors with cigar and books, by H. Walter Barnett [London], with signature of Mark Twain and inscription to Sir William Des Voent, [1900 April 6]; Photograph S
  - Photograph of oil portrait of Mark Twain by James MacNeil Whistler, with Whistler's butterfly signature, [1900]
  - Photograph of photograph of Mark Twain with Laura Hawkins Frazer, [1902 June]
  - Magazine clipping of 4 photographs of Mark Twain by Thomas E. Marr for "Three Famous Authors Outdoors," Ladies' Home Journal (November 1903), " Mark Twain at Quarry Hill Farm"; " Mark Twain lounging on porch with book upside down"; " Mark Twain with John L. Lewis "; " Mark Twain with his porcelain cat"; with photographs (four each) of William Dean Howells and Henry Van Dyke. 2 copies, Clipping
  - Two photographs of Mark Twain at Quarry Farm, and one photograph of the house at Quarry Farm, by T. E. Morr, published by the Curtis Company., [1903]
  - Clemens family photographs, [1903-1907]; 259 silver gelatin prints made in 2001 from original negatives taken by Mark Twain's daughter Jane.
    The photographs document Clemens family life including Twain, Jane, Clara, and Livy Clemens, pets, servants, friends including Richard Watson Gilmer, residences and a tour to Florence and Rome. #6314-bc
  - Photograph of postcard picture of Mark Twain smoking in bed, [1904]
  - Magazine photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing right, by Walter Barnett, [post 1904]; Clipping
  - Mark Twain, in black suit and bow tie, seated facing right with windows behind, by Apeda Studios, New York. With one polaroid copy, 190[4 or 7]
  - Color postcard of Mark Twain in bed, with caption " Mark Twain's Muse", [1904 -07]; Postcard
  - " Mark Twain, Pilot," watercolor portrait of Mark Twain at the helm of "American Humor" for Life, [1905]; Print
  - Magazine photograph of Mark Twain, in dark suit, by Florian; glued in center of xeroxed clipping re Olivia L. Clemens, [1906 February]; Clipping
  - 8 prints of photographs of Mark Twain, seated in rocker, with commentary on moral progress by Mark Twain and facsimile of Twain's letter on photographs from Dublin, N.H., [1906 September]
  - 8 prints of photographs of Mark Twain, seated in rocker, with commentary on moral progress by Mark Twain; framed, [1906 September]
  - Caricature of Mark Twain 1906 by "Fudge" ( George Frederick Scotson-Clark ), Watercolor
  - Print of stereograph of Mark Twain, standing, left profile, with Meerschaum pipe in right hand, by Underwood & Underwood, 1907; Clipping
  - Mark Twain, in academic costume, [post 1907 June 26]
  - Mark Twain, standing on porch in academic costume with house behind, [post 1907 June 26]
  - Mark Twain, in academic costume seated on porch, [post 1907 June 26]
  - Mark Twain, in white suit, seated indoors with book. With 1 copy, [post 1907 June 26]
  - Mark Twain, in white suit with pipe, standing at window, facing right, by gas fixture, [post 1907 June 26]
  - Mark Twain, in white suit, seated on rock with kitten, [post 1907 June 26]
  - Mark Twain in white suit in carved arm chair, sepia tone, rotogravure photo with caption. With one copy of photograph, [1907]
  - Mark Twain, in white suit facing forward, by A. F. Bradley, sepia tone. With polaroid copy, 1907
  - Mark Twain, playing billiards, [1908 January 2]
  - Mark Twain playing cards with Clara Clemens, [1908-1910]
  - Mark Twain seated at piano with Clara Clemens and Miss Nicol standing behind him, [1908-1910]
  - Clara Clemens, Ossip Gabrilowitsch, Mark Twain (in academic costume), Jervis Langdon, Jean Clemens, Joseph H. Twichell by Frank J. Sprague; photographed at Clara Clemens ' wedding; with AN on verso identifying people in photograph, 1909 October 6
  - Mark Twain, in academic costume outdoors by Frank J. Sprague; photographed at wedding of Clara Clemens; with AN on verso identifying photograph, 1909 October 6
  - Magazine photograph of Mark Twain, seated, right profile by Histed, with caption " Mark Twain. Died April 21st.", [1910]; Clipping
  - Stereoscopic photograph of the view of Elmira from Quarry Farm, [1931?]
  - Mark Twain, dressed in white, head and shoulders, facing right; sepia tone print signed by artist, Frank A Nankiwell, 1934; Print S
  - Mark Twain Centennial Medallion by Kileny; sculpted relief facing right inscribed " Samuel Langhorne Clemens, Mark Twain Centennial 1835-1935" and "Kileny" bottom left; on verso bottom Robbins & Co, Attleboro, MA. With photographs of medallion with an enlargement, and photograph of (Bernhardt) Wall etching of Mark Twain, box and envelope, Bronze Medallion
  - Mark Twain, in white suit, and Edward Quintard with signature of Mark Twain, in mat with missing left corner, Photograph S
  - Mark Twain, head and shoulder facing left, by Charles Watkins; with signature of Mark Twain and Samuel L. Clemens, Photograph S
  - Large framed photograph of Mark Twain, n.d.
  - Photograph of photograph of Mark Twain in black suit seated facing forward. 2 copies, n.d.
  - Photograph of photograph of Mark Twain in white suit seated with book in left hand. 2 glossy copies, 1 polaroid
  - Mark Twain in black suit with black bow tie, seated, with newspaper on lap. 1 glossy copy tightly cropped, 1 matte copy, n.d.
  - Mark Twain, head and shoulders facing right
  - Mark Twain, head and shoulders facing right by Newsboy, New York
  - Mark Twain, seated in study, by Pach Brothers, New York, n.d.
  - Pen and ink caricature of Mark Twain as a yachtsman by Harry Furness, with signature of artist, Sketch S
  - Mark Twain caricature for Vanity Fair, n.d.; Sketch
  - Color engraving of Mark Twain caricature with ANS humorous quote by Mark Twain, n.d.; Engraving
  - Mark Twain by Ben Morse with Mark Twain signature, n.d.; Inksketch S
  - Mark Twain, seated facing slightly left, cigar in left hand, with watch chain, by Mrs. Edward Ward, in heavy gold frame., Oil on canvas, 19 7/8" H X 16" W
  - Mark Twain, sculpted by "F.E.C.", n.d.; Bronze Wall Plaque
  - Mark Twain, head and shoulders facing right, engraving by Timothy Cole after a portrait by Abbott Henderson Thayer, with Mark Twain's signature, Engraving proof S
  - Print of engraving of Mark Twain, head and shoulders facing right, by Timothy Cole after a portrait by Abbott Henderson Thayer. 2 copies, Prints S
  - Photograph of drawing of Mark Twain in flames and urn
  - Print of etching of Mark Twain, head and shoulders; taken from unidentified book, Print
  - Print of photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing forward, by New York Photogravure, photo by Sarony, Print
  - Newspaper photograph of Mark Twain, in a dark suit, facing front, n.d.; Clipping
  - Unidentified girl, 3 views, facing right standing, facing forward seated, and standing, by Webster Art Gallery, Oakland, California, Photographs
  - Pen and ink sketch of Mark Twain on an ice floe, with an Eskimo, weighing relative value of fishing books versus money, by Dan Beard; pen and ink sketch on tan board, 1893; Illustration S (Box 8)
  - Tom Sawyer's Aunt Polly by J. G. Brown; monochrome oil on canvas; University of Virginia Art Index #77 1899, Painting, 76 x 115 cm., plus frame. (Box 8)
  - "The Assembly Was Dispossessed (Dispersed)" by B. West Clinedinst for Roughing It; black and white wash painting, 1899; Illustration S (Box 8)
  - Huck Finn in a dress with Jim in background by Edward Windsor Kemble for Adventures of Huckleberry Finn; pen and ink, 1899; Print (Box 8)
  - "Flies, Dan'l, Flies!" by Frederick Burr Opper for Sketches Old and New ("The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County") from Mark Twain uniform set; one print is signed by artist in pencil; one print taken from volume in uniform set, [1899]; Print S (Box 8)
  - "The Bathers at Leuke" by Thure Thulstrup for A Tramp Abroad; black and white wash on tan board, [1899]; Illustration S (Box 8)
  - "The Caravan" by Thure Thulstrup for A Tramp Abroad; black and white wash, [1899]; Illustration S (Box 8)
  - "An Unexpected Acquaintance" by Thure Thulstrup for A Tramp Abroad; black and white wash on tan board, [1899]; Illustration S (Box 8)
  - "I am the Dauphin, the Rightful King of France" by W. A. Rogers for Adventures of Huckleberry Finn; pen and ink, 1905 December 21; Illustration S (Box 8)
  - Illustration for Eve's Diary by Lester Ralph; pen and ink, [1906]; Drawing (Box 8)
  - "Three Years After the Battle" by Dan Beard for A Connecticut Yankee in King's Arthur's Court; pen and ink sketch in black and white; depicts skull and helmet with weeds, Illustration S (Box 8)
  - "The mate's shadow froze to the deck" by Arthur Burdett Frost; black and white print; signed by artist; taken from unidentified volume in Mark Twain uniform set, Print S (Box 8)
  - Kitchen scene with a black man, old man, woman and two boys by Arthur Burdett Frost; possibly for Adventures of Tom Sawyer, Print S (Box 8)
  - Black and white print of etching of riverside scene with cotton bales, boys and steam ship by Edmund H. Garrett; signed by artist, Print S (Box 8)
  - Two watercolor drawings by Fritz Kredel for Mark Twain translation of Slovenly Peter and two other watercolor drawings for an unidentified story, Watercolor (Box 8)
  - Mark Twain leaning against column reading an inscription by Peter Newell for Innocents Abroad; signed by artist; 7 copies, n.d.; Illustration S (Box 8)
  - Jim and Huck by F. Richardson for Adventures of Huckleberry Finn; autographs on recto of Mark Twain, Dan Beard, Bayard Jones, A. W. Drake, C. Word Blaisdell, A. B. Wengell, Edwin B. Child, and others, Illustration S (Box 8)
  - Illustration of a couple kissing by Seymour M. Stone; brown monotone; signed by artist, n.d.; Illustration S (Box 8)
  - "Never did Mark Twain make a more beautiful speech" ( Mark Twain surrounded by audience) by E. H. Ward; chalk and ink; audience includes Kate Douglas Smith Riggs Wiggin, Joseph H. Twichell, William Bliss Carman, Henry M. Alden, Ruth McEnery Stuart, Mary Wilkins Freeman, Henry H. Rogers, Sketch S (Box 8)
  - Illustration of an American tourist in Middle Eastern market by C. D. Weedon; signed by artist, n.d.; Colorprint S (Box 8)
  - 4 photographs of places associated with Mark Twain: "Interior Mark Twain Museum, Hannibal, Missouri "; " Mark Twain's mother's bedroom"; " Cardiff Hill, Hannibal, Missouri "; " Jervis Langdon, owner of Quarry Farm, Elmira, NY "; 3 stamped on verso " Life Photo by Dimitri Kessel " and all four marked Mark Twain's America, Photographs (Box 8)
  - Photograph of pilot's certificate issued to Mark Twain by District of St. Louis, Mo., 1859 April 9 (Box 8)
- Series V: Miscellaneous
  - Copy of Act of 1820 chapter 20 and Act of 1831 chapter 90 from Regis's Laws of Tennessee in hand of John Marshall Clemens, [post 1833]; AN, 2 p. (Box 8)
  - Clemens Family real estate notebooks1867-1868, Notebooks, total 97 p. (Box 8)
    Four notebooks numbered IV, VII, VII part 2, and VIII, concern the " Tennessee lands" owned by the Clemens family; they include copies of deed listings, descriptions of physical characteristics and natural resources of the area near Fentress County; a few comments about the people who lived there; brief mentions of events and neighbors; discussion of genealogy, horse thieves, and Union and Confederate sympathizers; and recipes for household needs, such as glue.
  - [Mark Twain] to [Pamela Clemens Moffett], St. Louis, MO, [1868 January 15]; A Envelope (Box 8)
    Franked William M. Stewart in Mark Twain's hand.
  - [Mark Twain] to [Mary Stotts Clemens ], [1868] February 22; A Envelope (Box 8)
    Franked William M. Stewart in Mark Twain's hand; with pencilled notes across the envelope in unknown hand.
  - Mark Twain, London, to Olivia L. Clemens, 1872 September 16; A Envelope (Box 8)
  - Mark Twain's note on Meisterschaft, [1880 n.d.]; AN, 1 p. (Box 8)
    "Anyway the children are too young."
  - Mark Twain's notes on family dramatizations of The Prince and the Pauper, 1884-1885; AN (Box 8)
  - "Zero Zephyrs," The Daily Gate City, 1884 January 6; Clipping (Box 8)
    About the coldest day in Keokuk, Iowa in 40 years; mentions William H. Bowman.
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to Franklin G. Whitmore, Hartford, CT, 1886 August 28; A Envelope (Box 8)
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Arthur Shipman, New Haven, CT, 1887 April 1; A Envelope (Box 8)
  - Mark Twain's notes on reviews of "Susy's Play", 1889; AN (Box 8)
  - [Pamela Clemens Moffett or Jane Lampton Clemens], Fredonia, NY, to Orion Clemens, [ante 1890]; A Envelope (Box 8)
  - [Olivia L. Clemens], Florence, Italy, to Clara Clemens, Berlin, 1892 December 22; A Envelope (Box 8)
  - With AN re stock shares of Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company stock held for Olivia L. Clemens, [1894 August 15]; A Envelope (Box 8)
  - Notes in unknown hand concerning Fredonia, NY, [post 1895]; AN, 4 p. (Box 8)
  - Mark Twain, Chelsea, England, to Frank Fuller, New York, 1897 June 2; A Envelope (Box 8)
  - [Mark Twain], Tuxedo Park, NY, to Jean Clemens, Katonah, NY, 1897 October 12; A Envelope (Box 8)
    With AN on envelope, "photo of child whispering."
  - Notes re publication of More Tramps Abroad ( Following the Equator ), [post 1897]; AN, 4 p. (Box 8)
    In unknown hands. In red ink "More Tramps Abroad"; in black ink, "American (sic) like to be latest Innocent Abroad"; with notes about word count and instructions from Olivia L. Clemens.
  - [Dolly Stanley], Vienna, to Clara Clemens, London, 1899 July 20; A Envelope (Box 8)
  - [Mark Twain] to Frank Fuller, New York, 1900 August 20; A Envelope (Box 8)